Finding Aid for Museum of Art (University of Michigan) records, 1946-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Museum of Art (University of Michigan) records
1946-2003
University of Michigan. Museum of Art.
0475 Bimu C450 2
Established as a separate unit of the university in 1946, the University of Michigan Museum of Art serves as a research and teaching facility for the university and surrounding communities. The record group documents the museum's exhibitions and installations of the permanent collection and complementary interpretive programming. Records include exhibition files; executive committee minutes and director's correspondence; photographs; publicity files; and material related to the Museum Practice Program.
26.3 linear feet
691 GB
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of these records was transferred (Donor No. 3195 ) in 2003. Periodic additions are expected.
The records of Museum of Art are open roe research use with the exception of certain of certain administrative records that are closed in accord with university policy and applicable law. Closed files in the Museum of Art record group include:
Executive Officers Records -- Box 19
The collection contains audio tapes from which digital copies have been made. Source tapes are for staff use only. Audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
The University of Michigan Museum of Art (UMMA) houses the second largest art collection in the state of Michigan, offering a rich permanent collection supplemented by an active special exhibition program. In addition, the many and varying art collections assist in teaching at the university. The collections of Chinese and Japanese paintings and ceramics; Old Master and contemporary prints and drawings; and Whistler prints are particularly strong.
The museum was established in its present form in 1946. The University Regents declared in November 1945 that the Museum of Art and Archaeology be abolished and that two separate units (the Museum of Art and the Museum of Archaeology) take its place. At their January 1946 meeting, the Regents further stipulated that the Museum of Art be maintained as "a separate administrative unit for the purpose of collection, conservation, study and exhibition of works of art and the preparation of publications with respect thereunto." The university's art collections had their origins long before 1946, however. Early systematic collecting began in 1855 when Professor Henry S. Frieze purchased a number of art works, chiefly engravings and plaster casts, to illustrate his courses in classical art and archaeology. In 1862 Frieze was instrumental in acquiring the university's first significant original work of art, Randolph Rogers' Nydia, the Blind Flower Girl of Pompeii.
The collection grew sporadically in the following decades, in large part through gifts from individuals as well as from graduating classes. The Henry C. Lewis bequest came to the university in 1895 and contained more than four hundred paintings and other works of art. With a modest budget for acquisitions, the museum's first director, Jean Paul Slusser, maintained a focus on collecting modern painting, sculpture and graphics and was quite successful due to his aesthetic expertise, knowledge of the New York art market and connections with Ann Arbor art organizations. The collection was further supplemented by gifts, including the Carl F. Clarke bequest of French and American landscape paintings and the Margaret Watson Parker bequest in 1936 (transferred to the museum in 1954 and 1955) of more than 600 Asian and Western works including Japanese prints and paintings by James NcNeill Whistler. Dr. Walter R. Parker (Margaret's husband and professor of ophthalmology at the university) further bequeathed funds to house the collection and to support future acquisitions.
During the very early years, efforts were made to display the collections. In 1857-1858 they were housed in the North and South Colleges. Space was allocated in the no longer extant library (newly erected in 1883), but even with the additional space gained when the library was enlarged in 1898 the facility could not adequately accommodate the growing collections. In 1910 the collections were moved to Alumni Memorial Hall, sharing the building with the Fine Arts Department and the Alumni Association. The hall has undergone renovations on several occasions. In 1957-1958, a Unistrut system of internal scaffolding was designed by professor of architecture William Muschenheim and installed in the museum apse. This installation increased gallery space. The Unistrut installation was subsequently removed in the early 1970s. Remodeling in 1966-1967 created additional gallery space; modernized the museum's heating, cooling and lighting systems; and provided areas for storage and behind-the-scenes work. The Museum of Art became Alumni Memorial Hall's sole occupant at this time. In 2003, planning was begun for a major expansion designed to increase the building's capacity by 55,000 square feet, to be used for additional gallery space, an auditorium and classrooms, and for a complete renovation of the existing facility.
Important components of the UMMA's program were added as it continued to expand its exhibitions program. In the late 1950s director Charles Sawyer began presenting museum seminars which, by 1963, had developed into the Museum Practice Program. The program, continued through 1995, provided training for many budding professionals in the museum field and organized numerous successful exhibitions for the UMMA over the years. (The training of museum professionals was revived at the university in Fall 2003 when an interdisciplinary Museum Studies Program was created under the auspices of the Rackham School of Graduate Studies.) The Friends of the Museum of Art was founded in 1968. This group supports the UMMA's acquisitions and other programming. Under director Bret Waller, the Docent Program was established in 1975 to provide tours for school classes and other visitors.
Museum Directors
1946-1956 Jean Paul Slusser
1957-1972 Charles H. Sawyer
1973 Robert A. Yassin (acting)
1973-1980 Bret Waller
1980 Clifford Olds (acting)
1981-1988 Evan M. Maurer
1988-1989 Graham Smith (interim)
1990-1997 William Hennessey
1997-1998 Carole C. McNamara (interim)
1998-present James Christen Steward
Partial Listing of Museum Assistant Directors
1961-1963? Charles Chetham
1963-1964 Samuel Sachs II
1965-1969 Paul L. Grigaut
1970- Robert A. Yassin
1974-1978 John E. Holmes
1981?-1983 Jacquelyn Baas Slee
1981?- Mary Kujawski Roberts
1990-1996? Ellen A. (Nan) Plummer
1998-present Carole C. McNamara
The records of the University of Michigan Museum of Art document its exhibition program, administration and its educational function through the Museum Practice Program. The UMMA record group has been arranged into seven series: Exhibition Files, Executive Files, Photographs, Publicity, Museum Practice Program, Historical Background, and Docents. The records include correspondence, committee minutes, publicity material and photographs. Exhibit catalogs and other publications are described separately in the Museum of Art Publications finding aid.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Museum of Art.; University of Michigan. Museum Practice Program.; University of Michigan. Graduate Seminar in Museum Practice.; Art.; Art--Exhibitions.; Artists.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Art.; Art--Exhibitions.; Artists.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Exhibition Files, 1946-2003
  Exhibition Files (1946-2003; 18 linear ft.) are arranged chronologically by exhibition date. In some cases exhibitions were mounted in locations other than Alumni Memorial Hall. The Rackham Galleries were used on occasion and space in the undergraduate library held travelling exhibitions from 1957/1958 to 1975/1976. Researchers should note that undergraduate library (UGLI) exhibition files are sometimes interfiled with those held in Alumni Memorial Hall (AMH), but other years are filed separately, either before or after AMH exhibits. This listing of exhibitions should not be considered complete. Although it is fairly comprehensive, there are some exhibitions listed on annual schedules for which there is no file and, likewise, there are files for exhibitions which do not appear in annual schedules. When it was clearly identified that an organization other than UMMA organized and/or circulated an exhibition, its name appears in parentheses following the exhibition title and dates.
  Information within individual files varies greatly and may include any or all of the following: correspondence with curators, exhibition organizers, artists and lenders; checklists; gallery floor plans; labels and label copy; pamphlets; publicity material, e.g., newspaper and magazine clippings, press releases; research material and notes; photographs, installation shots and UMMA objects; and audio recordings of artists' lectures and symposia. Material pertaining to the monetary value of museum holdings (at UMMA or elsewhere) or to individual donors (when not otherwise made public) has been removed. When possible, photocopies of the original pages were made with dollar values and names removed. Exhibition catalogues, produced by the UMMA or otherwise, as well as other related printed material (e.g. invitations, brochures, posters) have been filed separately (see separate finding aid for UMMA publications).
  - 1946-1947
    - Schedule (Box 1)
    - "Pioneers of Modern Art In America" [Rackham Galleries], July 1-21, 1946 (Box 1)
      (American Federation of Arts)
    - "Water Colors by Dong Kingman & DeHirsh Margules,", October 4-27, 1946 (Box 1)
    - "Four Centuries of Tapestry Weaving,", November 5-December 1, 1946 (Box 1)
      (includes photograph)
    - "Prints by Georges Rouault,", December 4-20, 1946 (Box 1)
      (Galerie St. Etienne)
    - "African Negro Sculpture,", December 4-20, 1946 (Box 1)
      (American Association of University Women)
    - "'The New Spirit' (The Work of Le Corbusier),", January 8-26, 1947 (Box 1)
    - "Art of the Middle Ages,", January 8-26, 1947 (Box 1)
      (Silberman Galleries)
    - "Forty Modern Prints,", February 10-March 2, 1947 (Box 1)
      (Detroit Institute of Arts)
    - "Paintings by George Grosz,", February 21-March 14, 1947 (Box 1)
      (E. Weyhe Gallery)
    - "Paintings by Ben Zion,", March 18-April 2, 1947 (Box 1)
      (Bertha Schaefer Gallery)
    - "Maurice Sterne: Drawings,", April 27-May 18, 1947 (Box 1)
    - "Pedro Figari: Paintings,", May 1-25, 1947 (Box 1)
      (Council for Inter-American Cooperation)
    - "The Medieval Spirit,", May 23-June 20, 1947 (Box 1)
      (Life Photographic Exhibitions)
  - 1947-1948
    - Schedule (Box 1)
    - "Brooklyn Museum First National Print Annual,", July 1-21, 1947 (Box 1)
    - "Vanguard Group,", July 1-28, 1947 (Box 1)
    - "Modern Handmade Jewelry,", September 30-October 19, 1947 (Box 1)
      (Museum of Modern Art)
    - "Competition for Printed Fabrics,", October 7-26, 1947 (Box 1)
      (CANCELLED)
    - "Fine Arts Under Fire,", October 12-30, 1947 (Box 1)
    - "Paintings Looted from Holland,", November 13-28, 1947 (Box 1)
      (Albright Art Gallery)
    - "American Abstract Artists,", December 2-21, 1947 (Box 1)
      (Western Association of Art Museum Directors)
    - "Lasansky and Iowa Print Group,", December 2-31, 1947 (Box 1)
    - "European Posters,", January 6-18, 1948 (Box 1)
    - "Prints by Matisse and Picasso,", January 6-18, 1948 (Box 1)
    - "Fifty Latin American Prints,", February 1-12, 1948 (Box 1)
      (IBM Corporation)
    - "26th Annual National Exhibition of Advertising Art,", February 15-March 7, 1948 (Box 1)
    - "The Painter Looks at People,", March 9-28, 1948 (Box 1)
    - "John Brown Series: Jacob Lawrence,", March 9-28, 1948 (Box 1)
    - "Prints by Lovis Corinth,", April 25-May 9, 1948 (Box 1)
    - "Creative Design and the Consumer (Container Corporation of America),", April 25-May 16, 1948 (Box 1)
    - "Water Colors by John Marin,", May 11-30, 1948 (Box 1)
      (Columbus Gallery of Fine Arts)
  - 1948-1949
    - Schedule (Box 1)
    - "Art Masterworks: University Loan Print Collection,", July 29-August 12, 1948 (Box 1)
      (Audio-Visual Education Center)
    - "Student Loan Prints,", September 12-25, 1948 (Box 1)
    - "Newberry Collection of Drawings and Water Colors,", September 28-October 24, 1948 (Box 1)
      (John S. Newberry, Jr.?)
    - "The Graphic Circle,", September 28-October 24, 1948 (Box 1)
      (Jacques Seligmann & Co., Inc.)
    - "Michigan on Canvas" [Rackham Galleries], October 28-November 11, 1948 (Box 1)
      (J.L. Hudson Company)
    - "Contemporary Paintings from the Albright Art Gallery,", November 4-24, 1948 (Box 1)
    - "Americana: The Index of American Design,", November 28-December 27, 1948 (Box 1)
    - "Ancient Peruvian Textiles,", December 5-28, 1948 (Box 1)
    - "Work in Progress in Michigan,", January 6-26, 1949 (Box 1)
    - "Egypt,", February 13-March 6, 1949 (Box 1)
    - "Recent Accessions,", February 13-March 6, 1949 (Box 1)
    - "Five American Painters,", March 1-22, 1949 (Box 1)
    - "Forty Drawings from the Museum of Modern Art,", March 14-April 4, 1949 (Box 1)
    - "Max Beckmann,", April 12-May 1, 1949 (Box 1)
      (Buchholz Gallery)
    - "American Printmaking, 1913-1947,", May 7-28, 1949 (Box 1)
    - "18th Century England,", May 1-28, 1949 (Box 1)
    - "L. Moholy-Nagy Memorial Exhibition,", May 10-31, 1949 (Box 1)
    - "Michigan Water Color Society, Third Annual,", June 4-July 3, 1949 (Box 1)
  - 1949-1950
    - Schedule (Box 1)
    - "Islamic Miniature Painting,", July 13-August 3, 1949 (Box 1)
    - "Student Loan Prints,", September 8-28, 1949 (Box 1)
    - "Jazz by Henri Matisse,", October 2-23, 1949 (Box 1)
    - "Hayter's Five Personages,", October 2-23, 1949 (Box 1)
    - "1848 Year of Revolutions,", October 10-November 7, 1949 (Box 1)
    - "New American Painters,", November 7-27, 1949 (Box 1)
    - "Contemporary American Painters,", November 7-27, 1949 (Box 1)
      (Museum of Cranbrook Academy of Art)
    - "Art Privately Owned in Ann Arbor,", December 1-31, 1949 (Box 1)
      (Ann Arbor Art Association)
    - "Accessions, 1949,", January 7-February 1, 1950 (Box 1)
    - "Work in Progress in Michigan,", January 7-28, 1950 (Box 1)
    - "Eugène Atget's Magic Lens,", February 19-March 15, 1950 (Box 1)
    - "The Arts Work Together,", February 19-March 15, 1950 (Box 1)
    - "Brooklyn Museum Third Print Annual,", March 1-22, 1950 (Box 1)
    - "Sam Haile Pottery,", March 30-April 7, 1950 (Box 1)
    - "Chinese Buddhist Bronzes,", April 13-May 7, 1950 (Box 1)
    - "Painting Toward Architecture,", April 23-May 14, 1950 (Box 1)
      (Miller Company)
      (includes labels)
    - "Far Eastern Art,", May 16-June 18, 1950 (Box 1)
    - "Howard Cook-Graphic Work,", May 16-June 18, 1950 (Box 1)
      (includes correspondence with the artist)
    - "Student Sculpture,", June 9-18, 1950 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1951
    - Schedule and gallery talks (Box 1)
    - "Modern Graphic Art,", July 2-30, 1950 (Box 1)
    - "Art Schools, U.S.A., 1949,", October 1-22, 1950 (Box 1)
    - "A New Direction in Intaglio: The Work of Mauricio Lasansky and His Students,", October 15-November 5, 1950 (Box 1)
      (Walker Art Center)
    - "Sport and Circus,", November 9-29, 1950; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - "Work in Progress in Michigan,", December 4-31, 1950 (Box 1)
    - "Water Colors and Drawings from the Collection of John S. Newberry,", December 4-31, 1950 (Box 1)
      (John S. Newberry?)
    - "Student Printmaking,", December 9, 1950-January 5, 1951 (Box 1)
    - "Society Anonyme Collection" (Yale University Art Gallery), January 8-29, 1951 (Box 1)
    - "Michigan Water Color Society,", January 8-29, 1951 (Box 1)
    - "Portraits-Museum Collection,", February 4-March 12, 1951 (Box 1)
    - "Art Privately Owned in Ann Arbor,", February 12-March 7, 1951 (Box 1)
    - "Kyoto,", February 23-March 11, 1951 (Box 1)
      (includes photographs)
    - "Modern Furniture,", March 4-April 4, 1951 (Box 2)
      (includes installation photographs)
    - "Accessions, 1950,", March 10-April 4, 1951 (Box 2)
    - "Third Annual Student Arts Festival Exhibit,", March 18-April 4, 1951 (Box 2)
    - "Medieval Indian Sculpture,", April 9-May 2, 1951 (Box 2)
      (includes pamphlets)
    - "Lifar Collection of Ballet Designs and Costumes,", May 2-27, 1951 (Box 2)
    - "Contemporary Italian Drawings,", May 4-31, 1951 (Box 2)
    - "Student Exhibit: College of Architecture and Design,", June 10-27, 1951 (Box 2)
  - 1951-1952
    - Schedule (Box 2)
    - "Master Prints from the Rosenwald Collection,", July 1-15, 1951 (Box 2)
    - "Painters of the Northwest,", July 1-22, 1951 (Box 2)
    - "Moholy-Nagy (Water Colors and Prints),", July 1-22, 1951 (Box 2)
      (Circle Gallery)
    - "Summer Exhibits-Museum Collections,", July 18-September 28, 1951 (Box 2)
    - "Age of Enlightenment,", October 1-25, 1951 (Box 2)
    - "Faculty Exhibition: College of Architecture and Design,", October 3-25, 1951 (Box 2)
    - "Faculty Exhibition,", January 13-February 12, 1952 (Box 2)
      (exhibition loaned to Kalamazoo Institute of Arts)
    - "Seattle Drawings,", October 6-26, 1951 (Box 2)
      (Seattle Art Museum)
    - "Italian, Spanish and French Paintings of the 17th and 18th Centuries,", November 1-28, 1951; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - "Old Master Drawings and Prints-Museum Collection,", November 1-December 31, 1951 (Box 2)
    - "Three Modern Styles,", December 4-24, 1951 (Box 2)
    - "Work in Progress in Michigan,", December 4-24, 1951 (Box 2)
    - "Drawings from the Museum Collection,", January 2-27, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Mariska Karasz: Abstractions with Thread,", January 6-27, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Photographs of American Architecture" (Wayne Andrews), January 8-27, 1952 (Box 2)
      (Michigan Museum Council)
    - "Venice,", February 1-28, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Four Centuries of French Prints,", February 5-26, 1952 (Box 2)
      (George Binet Print Collection)
    - "Tapestries and Paintings-Museum Collection,", February 5-March 5, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Inter-Arts Union Fourth Annual Exhibition,", March 9-27, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Advancing French Art,", March 1-23, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Peiping,", March 1-23, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Accessions to the Museum Collections,", April 1-25, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Paintings by Hortense M. Gordon,", April 6-25, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Student Exhibition: College of Architecture and Design,", May 1-25, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "1st Michigan Regional Art Exhibition" [Rackham Galleries], May 15-31, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Sixth Annual Michigan Water Color Society,", June 1-29, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Paintings from the Permanent Collection,", June 1-29, 1952 (Box 2)
  - 1952-1953
    - Schedule and gallery talks (Box 2)
    - "The Artist's Viewpoint,", July 7-28, 1952 (Box 2)
      (part of the "Modern Views of Man and Society" summer session)
    - "The City,", July 7-28, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Paintings from the Whitney Museum of American Art,", July 7-28, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Hokusai School Drawings,", September 28-November 2, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Japanese Festival,", October 12-November 2, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Europe: The New Generation,", November 9-30, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Southwestern Textiles and Retablos,", November 9-30, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Lithographs Plain and Colored,", December 4-31, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Process of Hand Lithography,", December 4-31, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Drawings by Americans-Museum Collections,", December 4-31, 1952 (Box 2)
    - "Contemporary Italian Prints,", January 6-27, 1953 (Box 2)
    - "Prints by Hiroshi Yoshida,", January 6-February 3, 1953 (Box 2)
    - "'Ten Bamboo' and 'Mustard Seed Garden' Prints,", January 6-February 3, 1953 (Box 2)
    - "Sculpture in Progress,", February 8-March 1, 1953 (Box 2)
    - "Calligraphic and Geometric,", February 8-March 1, 1953 (Box 2)
    - "Klee Drawings,", February 8-March 1, 1953 (Box 2)
    - "Staff Artists of the Big Ten,", March 4-25, 1953 (Box 2)
      (Michigan State College)
    - "Fifth Inter-Arts Festival Exhibit,", March 8-29, 1953 (Box 2)
    - "Old Master Drawings-Museum Collections,", March-April 1953 (Box 2)
    - "Early Chinese Jades,", March 22-April 22, 1953 (Box 2)
    - "Paintings, Drawings-Museum Collections,", March 27-April 28, 1953 (Box 2)
    - "Accessions-1952,", April 2-28, 1953 (Box 2)
    - "Modern Bible Illustration,", April 7-28, 1953 (Box 2)
    - "Student Exhibition-College of Architecture and Design,", May 3-31, 1953 (Box 2)
    - "Museum Collections,", June 7-28, 1953 (Box 2)
  - 1953-1954
    - Schedule (Box 2)
    - "Popular Art in America,", June 30-August 7, 1953 (Box 2)
      (part of the "Popular Arts in America" summer session)
    - "California Water Color Society,", July 1-August 1, 1953 (Box 2)
    - "Summer Museum Collections,", July-September 1953 (Box 2)
    - "Swedish Textiles,", September 15-October 15, 1953 (Box 2)
      (Smithsonian Institution: National Collection of Fine Arts)
    - "Eskimo Carvings,", October 4-25, 1953 (Box 2)
      (Canadian Handicrafts Guild and Eskimo Art, Inc.)
    - "Recent French Art Exhibition Posters,", October 4-25, 1953 (Box 2)
    - "Purcell and Elmslie: Architects,", October 18-November 3, 1953 (Box 2)
    - "Framing-Right and Wrong,", October 30-November 20, 1953 (Box 2)
      (The House of H. Heydenryk, Jr.)
    - "Michigan Printmakers Society,", November 1-18, 1953 (Box 2)
    - "Fleischman Collection of American Paintings,", November 15-December 6, 1953 (Box 2)
      (includes correspondence with the lender)
    - "A Half Century of Picasso,", November 29-December 30, 1953 (Box 2)
    - "Memorable LIFE Photographs,", December 10-30, 1953 (Box 2)
    - "Water Colors and Drawings by Gavarni,", January 2-24, 1954 (Box 2)
      (Smithsonian Institution)
    - "Callot, Goya and Van Ostade: Prints from the Museum Collection,", January 2-February 1, 1954 (Box 2)
    - "19th and 20th Century French Prints-Museum Collection,", January 2-February 1, 1954 (Box 2)
    - "Persian-Hindu Miniatures" (Portland Art Museum), January 3-24, 1954 (Box 2)
    - "Museum of Art Collects,", January 27-February 28, 1954 (Box 2)
    - "Student Printmakers,", February 1-17, 1954 (Box 2)
    - "African Sculptures,", February 7-28, 1954 (Box 2)
      (Segy Gallery)
    - "The Embellished Surface,", February 7-March 1, 1954 (Box 2)
    - "Bird Sculptures,", February 20-March 10, 1954 (Box 2)
      (Washtenaw County Audubon Society)
    - "Flaherty Photographs,", February 21-March 7, 1954 (Box 2)
      (Robert Flaherty Foundation)
    - "Beckmann and Rouault,", March 7-28, 1954 (Box 3)
    - "The Story of Glass Decoration,", March 15-April 4, 1954 (Box 3)
      (Corning Museum of Glass)
    - "Accessions-1953,", April 4-May 2, 1954 (Box 3)
    - "Paintings by Josef Albers" (Sidney Janis Gallery), April 11-May 2, 1954 (Box 3)
      (University of Redlands, California)
    - "Original Drawings for Book Illustrations,", April 11-May 2, 1954 (Box 3)
    - "Student Exhibition-College of Architecture and Design,", May 6-26, 1954 (Box 3)
  - 1954-1955
    - Schedule (Box 3)
    - "Three Women Painters: Irene Rice Pereira, Kay Sage, Dorothea Tanning,", June 20-July 25, 1954 (Box 3)
      (part of the "Woman in the World of Man" summer session)
    - "Woman as Subject, Woman as Artist-Museum Collections,", June 20-September 7, 1954 (Box 3)